Casatelli, Jeanne; Papers apap150
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Jeanne Casatelli Papers
1966-2002
1996-2002
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Casatelli, Jeanne
apap150
2.6 cubic ft. 6 Digital Files 4 videotapes
Jeanne Casatelli is a native of East Greenbush, New York, who has fought sprawl in her hometown for more than twenty years.
Biographical History
Jeanne Casatelli is a native of East Greenbush, New York, who has fought sprawl in her hometown for more than twenty years. She is a founding member of East Greenbush's Community Action Network, a grassroots organization whose stated purpose is "to promote good planning and the protection of natural, historic, and civic resources in accordance with principles espoused as Smart Growth, New Urbanism, and Quality Community." (Community Action Network of East Greenbush Statement of Purpose, undated, Series 2, Box 1, Folder 5.)
One of CAN's most visible activities was their campaign to prevent the widening of a stretch of U.S. Route 9 and 20, also known as the Columbia Turnpike, which passes through East Greenbush. New York's Department of Transportation (DOT) wanted to widen the road by a total of 34 feet, converting it from four lanes to five lanes. Casatelli and CAN argued that DOT's plan was not in keeping with new regulations that favored context sensitive design for highway projects, nor with the recommendations of Lt. Governor Mary Donahue's Quality Communities Task Force. CAN saw the rebuilding of Route 9 and 20 as an opportunity to develop a community-oriented "main street" in the suburban town of East Greenbush, which lacked a traditional town center. They argued that the road could be redesigned to comply with DOT's safety requirements without being widened to five lanes, and sought the input of nationally-renowned highway designers to support their position. CAN's campaign was unsuccessful, and the road was widened.
Casatelli is also involved in Citizens for Riverfront Action, an organization dedicated to protecting and providing access to the Hudson River in Rensselaer.
Scope and Contents
The papers document Casatelli's interest in issue-based grassroots organizations in the late 1990s and early 2000s through her involvement in Community Action Network (CAN). CAN opposed the widening of U.S. Route 9 and 20 in East Greenbush through a vigorous campaign of public education and political action. The papers provide near-complete documentation of this campaign, including letters, e-mail, press releases, position papers, contact lists, and notes.
Information on another organization of which Casatelli was a member, Citizens for Riverfront Action (CRA), is limited to CRA's involvement in coordinating Scenic Hudson's Great River Sweep in the community of Rensselaer.
Not included in this collection are Casatelli's files on CAN's effort to save the Defreest-Church house from destruction by developers. The house, which was constructed in the 1830s, was eligible for inclusion on the National Register of Historic Places because of its links to the Anti-Rent War of the mid 1800s. It was demolished in November 2002 to make way for a Target store parking lot. Casatelli transferred her files on the Defreest-Church house to the Sierra Club Atlantic Chapter for use in potential litigation.
Since both CAN and CRA are grassroots organizations, there is virtually no information on organizational structure or membership, and no formal records of meetings. One exception is an undated statement of purpose for CAN in Series 2, Box 1, Folder 5.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into five file series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Jeanne Casatelli, 2002 November
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Environmental protection -- New York (State).; Highway planning -- New York (State) -- Citizen participation.; Highway engineering -- New York (State).; Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.); East Greenbush (N.Y.: Town); Rensselaer County (N.Y.); Clippings.; Videocassettes.; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Notes.; Press releases.; Fliers (printed matter); Conservation and the Environment; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Rensselaer County, New York; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Digital Files; Community Action Network of East Greenbush (N.Y.); Citizens for Riverfront Action.; Scenic Hudson (Organization)
- Route 9 and 20, 1997-2002; 1; 1 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes extensive correspondence, e-mail, press releases, position papers, notes, and other documents related to CAN's campaign against the widening of Route 9 and 20. Much of the correspondence is outgoing and addressed to political leaders, including Governor George Pataki, Lt. Governor Mary Donahue, State Senator Joseph Bruno and his staff, and East Greenbush Town Supervisor Bob Angelini. There is also some correspondence with highway engineers from whom Casatelli sought support for a redesign of NYS-DOT's plan for Route 9 and 20. Several folders contain printed copies of e-mail. Most of these e-mails do not contain full headers with date and recipient information. In many cases it is impossible to determine when or to whom individual e-mails were sent. At the end of the series are several oversized items, including posters and a map reflecting community ideas for the redesign of Route 9 and 20.
  - Addresses of Homes and Business on Route 9 and 20, Undated (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 1)
  - Conceptual Stage Relocation Plan, U.S Route 9 and 20, ca. 1997 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 2)
  - Contact List, ca. 1998-ca. 2001 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1999 January-June (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1999 July-December (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 2001 January-February (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 2001 March-April (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 2001 May-June (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 2001 July-December (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 2002 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - Department of Transportation, 1998-1999 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 13)
  - Department of Transportation, Route 9 and 20 Newsletter, Issue 3, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 14)
  - E-Mail, 1999-2002 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 15)
  - E-Mail, 1999-2002 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 16)
  - E-Mail, Undated (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 17)
  - E-Mail, Undated (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 18)
  - Final Design Report/ Environmental Assessment, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 19)
  - Notes, ca. 1998-ca. 2001 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 20)
  - Notes, ca. 1998-ca. 2001 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 21)
  - Parcel Maps - Route 9 and 20 Properties, Undated (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 22)
  - Petitions, 1997-2001 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 23)
  - Position Papers, Fact Sheets, and Fliers, 1998-2001 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 24)
  - Press Releases, 1997-2001 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 25)
  - Project Location Map, Undated (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 26)
  - Proposal Buildout Images, Undated (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 27)
  - Proposal and Placement Plan, First Draft of Colombia Turnpikes Transportation Management System, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 28)
  - Public Hearing on 9 and 20 Proposal - Transcript, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 29)
  - Report from the Public on the Rt. and 20/Colombia Turnpike Project, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 30)
  - Signalized Intersections Input Worksheets, Undated (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 31)
  - Survey of Route 9 and 20 Business Owners, Undated (Box 1 (1-Route 9 and 20), Folder 32)
  - Community Action Network, Route 9 and 20 Posters, Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
  - Route 9 and 20, Maps and Plans, Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 2)
- Subject Files, 1966-2002; 2; 1 cubic ft.
  This series contains files on various areas of concern to Casatelli and the activist groups with which she was involved. There is extensive information on topics relevant to the campaign against Route 9 and 20, such as road design, smart growth, and suburban sprawl. Other subjects include the Hudson River, waterfront access in Rensselaer County, and East Greenbush political life.
  There is one folder on Scenic Hudson's Great River Sweep. The River Sweep was a grassroots event coordinated by volunteers in local communities along the Hudson River. Volunteers from these communities cooperated to remove debris from the river. Casatelli and her Citizens for Riverfront Action coordinated the Great River Sweep in Rensselaer from 1998-2000. The Scenic Hudson Great River Sweep folder contains correspondence, press releases, financial records, and other documents related to the local River Sweep.
  - Articles - Miscellaneous, 1998-2001; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - BASF, 2002; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Capital District Transportation Committee, 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Community Action Network of East Greenbush, Statement of Purpose, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Community Image Survey, 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Context Sensitive Design, 1998-1999; 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Contributors to Senator Joseph Bruno's Campaign, 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Defreestville Area Neighborhoods Association, 2000; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - East Greenbush, Boat Launch, 1997-2000 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - East Greenbush, Politics, 1999, 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Energy, Alternative Sources, 2000 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Friends of Hudson/St. Lawrence Cement Project, 2002 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - A Good Place To Live, Terry Pundell, Excerpts, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Greater Capital Region Teacher Center, 1995; 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Healthy Heart Program, New York State Department of Health, 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Hudson River and Hudson River Valley, 1995-2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, ca. 1996-ca. 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - National Register of Historic Places, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - New York State Department of State, Publications, 1998; 2000 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - New York State Governor's Office, Press Releases, 1998; 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - New York State, History and Facts, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - New York State Tourism, Brochures, and Postcards, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Northern Adirondack Revitalization Initiative, Briefing Paper, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Planning Commissioners' Journal, Articles, 1992-1994; 1996-1997 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Project for Public Spaces, Inc., 2000 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Property Rights Foundation of America, 2000 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - Quality Coasts, Quality Communities, Waterfront Rediscovery Conference, 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 27)
  - Quality Communities, Demonstration Program and Task Force, 2000-2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - Quality Communities, Quality Coasts Conference, Brochure, 2002 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - Rensselaer, 1996-2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - Rensselaer County 1791-1966, Excerpts, ca. 1966 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 31)
  - "Rensselaer: The Right Side of the River" Campaign, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 32)
  - Rensselaer Waterfront, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 33)
  - Riverview Road, Rexford, 1999 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 34)
  - Road Design, 1984; 1997-1999; 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 35)
  - Scenic Hudson, Great River Sweep, 1998-2000; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 36)
  - Smart Growth, 1995-2002; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 37)
  - Smart Growth, Urban Advantage, ca. 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 38)
  - Surface Transportation Policy Project, 1996; 1998; 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 39)
  - Urban Design Group, ca. 2000 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 40)
  - Walkable Communities Inc, ca. 2000 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 41)
  - Walkable Communities, Slide Presentation, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 42)
  - Website Printouts - Miscellaneous, 2001 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 43)
  - Westchester Land Trust, 2001; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 44)
- News Clippings, ca. 1996-ca. 2002; 3; 0.4 cubic ft. (Box 1 (Jeanne Casatelli Papers))
  Partially processed; not arranged
  This series consists of news clippings on topics of interest to Casatelli. Duplicates have been removed from the series, but the clippings have not been arranged further. Many clippings relate to the Route 9 and 20 widening issue. Sources for the clippings include the Albany Times-Union, the Rensselaer Beacon, and the Independent. There are also some clippings on highway design and other environmental issues from newspapers in other regions, as well as clippings on Scenic Hudson's Great River Sweep event.
- Photographs and Moving Images, ca. 1999-2001; 4; 0.2 cubic ft.
  Arranged by format
  This series contains four VHS videocassettes, 29 color snapshots depicting Route 9 and 20 in East Greenbush. Although the photographs are undated, they probably date from 1999-2001.
  - Photographs of Routes 9 and 20, East Greenbush [29 items], ca. 1999-2001 (Box 1 (4-Photographs and Moving Images), Item 1)
  - Rennselaer [sic] River Sweep and Urban Sprawl," VHS Videocassette, 2000 (Box 2 (4-Photographs and Moving Images), Item 1)
  - "Route #303 The Visioning Process: Smart Growth and Public Health," 2 VHS Videocassettes, Undated (Box 2 (4-Photographs and Moving Images), Item 2)
  - "Scenic Hudson: The Great River Sweep," VHS Videocassette, Roadrunner Production Services, Undated (Box 2 (4-Photographs and Moving Images), Item 3)
- Electronic Records, 2000-2001; 5; 6 Digital Files
  This series is comprised of three PowerPoint presentations and three video clips, most of which are related to a community-oriented sustainable development study on Route 303 in Rockland County, New York. It is likely that Casatelli saw this study as a model, which could be applied to redesigning Route 9 and 20. The two video clips on Route 303 duplicate footage found on the Route 303 video in series 4. The third video clip is a brief interview of Don Chen, founding director of Smart Growth America. The sound is very low in this clip and difficult to hear.
  The files were originally located on two recordable compact discs. They have been copied to a University Libraries' server for preservation reasons.
  - "303." "The Route 303 Sustainable Development Study, Rockland County, New York." 7 min., 36 sec. Copyright 2000, Rockland County., 2000 May 31 (Last Modified) (Mpeg 1)
  - "303Charette." "Route 303 Sustainable Development Study: The Visioning Process." 6 min., 20 sec., 2000 February 5 (Last Modified) (Mpeg 2)
  - Untitled file. Interview of Don Chen, founding director, Smart Growth America, 2 min, 5 sec., Undated (Avi 3)
  - "Charette Presentation." Microsoft PowerPoint file. 24 slides., 2000 April 21 (Last Modified) (Ppt 1)
  - "Route 303 Challenges Presentation." Microsoft PowerPoint file. 18 slides., 2000 April 20 (Last Modified) (Ppt 2)
  - "Route 303 Slideshow." Microsoft PowerPoint file. 18 slides., 2000 April 20 (Last Modified) (Ppt 3)